Maren Lockwood Carden Papers on the Oneida Community
Maren Lockwood Carden Papers on the Oneida Community
1960-2000
Carden, Maren Lockwood.
1 linear ft.
Notes, drafts and research material created or collected by Carden for her book on the Oneida Community.
4123205
Biographical History
Maren Lockwood Carden is an American author, sociologist and feminist. Educated at the University of Maryland (M.A., 1957) and Harvard University (Ph.D., 1963), she is the author of numerous books, papers and articles on the Oneida Community, communal societies, and women's studies.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Maren Lockwood Carden Papers on the Oneida Community consists of research notes, correspondence, interview notes, conference papers, and drafts of papers and chapters, all relating to Carden's study of the Oneida Community. Carden's original folders and folder titles were retained; in the few cases where items were not foldered, titles have been assigned. These are indicated by square brackets [ ].
Arrangement of the Collection
Folders are in alphabetical order.
Related Material
See also the
Oneida Community Collection
for more of Carden's research, including interviews with members of the community.
has extensive holdings relating to the Oneida Community and to Utopian communities in general. Please refer to to locate additional manuscript collections, and to to locate books, pamphlets, serials and other items which are cataloged in the Rare Books Collection.
A larger collection of Carden's papers is held by Harvard University Library, accession number: 81-M210.
Separated Material
One roll of microfilm, containing the A. J. Macdonald Papers, has been separately cataloged.
Subject and Genre Headings
Activism and social reform; New York State; Religion and philosophy; Carden, Maren Lockwood.; Noyes, P. Geoffrey.; Branch Davidians.; Oneida Community.; Oneida, ltd.; Collective settlements -- United States.; Family-owned business enterprises.; Intentional communities -- New York (State); Oneida (N.Y.) -- History.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Lectures.; Interviews.; Research notes.; Sociologists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Maren Lockwood Carden, 2014.
Inventory
- [Files]
  - [Branch Davidians and Oneida - notes on similarities and differences], [circa 1993-1994?] (Box 1)
  - Census of 1908 and 1961, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Chap III rewritten Sept 68 (Box 1)
  - Communal Studies Association paper on Oneida, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Conference on NYS History, Jun 1998; includes copy of paper presented (Box 1)
  - [Conference on NYS History], 1999; includes copy of paper presented (Box 1)
  - Conference organized by Kathman, 1993; includes copy of paper presented (Box 1)
  - Conference, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Conference Elderhostel paper, 1996; 1997 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1977; 1984,; 1988,; 1991-2000,; undated; includes Richard Kathmann, Mansion House (Box 1)
  - Data, 1993 (Box 1)
  - [Drafts, unidentified] (Box 1)
  - Encycl. NYS (Box 1)
  - Encyclopedia NYS Oneida (Box 1)
  - Interviews by telephone, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Interviews, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Interviews compilation (Box 2)
  - Interviews not typed up, [1960s?] (Box 2)
  - Management positions [in Oneida] (Box 2)
  - New Zealand, 1996; includes correspondence, notes, drafts for conference presentation (Box 2)
  - [Notes], [1960s]; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Noyes, Geoff collection + notes, MLC (Box 2)
  - Noyes, Hilda collection and notes, etc. (Box 2)
  - [Proposal for interpretive plan for Mansion House] (Box 2)
  - Reviews/comments thesis & book (Box 2)
  - Statistical analyses (Box 2)
  - Strays (Box 2)
  - [Miscellany] (Box 2)